Roy Elmer Beck collection, Inclusive: 1918-1946, undated, Bulk: 1918-1919, 1936-1946
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Roy Elmer Beck collection
Inclusive: 1918-1946, undated, Bulk: 1918-1919, 1936-1946
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
3293
Beck, Roy Elmer, 1885 - 1944
7 folders.
The Roy Elmer Beck collection contains materials from Beck's lengthy employment for the Texas Electric Railway Company in Waco.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Roy Elmer Beck, the son of William Franklin Beck and Amanda Louise Harp, was born in Midlothian, Texas, on 1885 June 25. He married Elizabeth Lethella Howell on 1919 December 23 and together they had one daughter named Hester Mae Beck Willis.
For 35 years of their marriage, the Becks lived in Waco, Texas. Roy found steady employment as a conductor for the Texas Electric Railway Company. Also known as the “Interurban,” this company was formed in 1917 to connect some of the larger cities of Central Texas and to facilitate the movement of passengers and goods throughout the region. Beck worked for the railway for 28 years, traveling primarily between Dallas and Waco. Many of the materials found in this collection originated from Roy's experiences working for the railroad.
Roy Elmer Beck passed away on 1944 August 25. He, along with his wife Elizabeth, were buried in Oakwood Cemetery. Due to the advent of the automobile industry and the interstate highway system, the Texas Electric Railway Company began to face severe financial struggles. Executives decided to cease streetcar operations in Waco by the winter of 1948.
Scope and Content
The materials in the Roy Elmer Beck collection range in date from 1918 to 1946, with most of them originating in the 1930's and 1940's. The majority of the materials stem from Beck's employment for the Texas Electric Railway Company, but personal items such as Selective Service registration cards and a poll tax receipt are also in the collection.
Series I. Correspondence contains letters from the Texas Electric Railway Company, primarily concerning employee tax rates. Series II. Financial Documents consists of receipts from the Beck family, mainly from household utilities. Series III. Literary Productions, the largest series in the collection, covers a wide range of materials including Roy Beck's Selective Service registration card from 1918, a stock certificate in the Texas Electric Railway Company, and various railroad forms.
Arrangement
Prior to the current arrangement, the materials in this collection were housed in a single folder with no title or date range. Some of the older documents had already been sleeved, and most of the collection was in good condition.
The collection is now arranged into three series according to material type: Series I. Correspondence, Series II. Financial Documents, and Series III. Literary Productions.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 3293. Acquired 1997-02-00
Related Resources
Related references
Find A Grave, Inc. "Roy Elmer Beck." Memorial #68062018. Databases. Accessed 2017 March 8.
Ryan, Terri Jo. "Interurban Railway." Waco History.org. Accessed 2017 March 8.
Webb, Walter Prescott. "Interurban Line." Handbook of Waco and McLennan County Texas. Edited by Dayton Kelley. Waco: Texian Press, 1972.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Beck, Roy Elmer, 1885-1944.
Subjects (Organizations)
Texas Electric Railway.
Subjects
Railroads -- Texas.
Genres
Correspondence.; Financial records.
- Correspondence, 1939-1942; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  Series I. Correspondence consists of letters sent by the Texas Electric Railway Company to their employees. These deal primarily with income and Social Security tax deductions.
  - Texas Electric Railway Company, 1939-1942 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Financial Documents, 1919-1946; 2
  Series II. Financial Documents contains receipts procured by Roy Elmer Beck and his wife Elizabeth. Most of the items relate to household utilities such as power, gas, and water. There is also a poll tax receipt that Elizabeth received from an election in McLennan County in 1946.
  - Receipts: Beck Family, 1919-1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Literary Productions, 1918-1944, undated; 3
  Series III. Literary Productions comprises the bulk of the collection. Its materials deal primarily with Roy Beck's employment at the Texas Electric Railway Company. The series also contains Roy Beck's Selective Service registration card from a local McLennan County draft board in 1918.
  - Blank Forms and Receipts: Texas Electric Railway Company, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Passes and Tickets: Texas Electric Railway Company, 1936-1944 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Selective Service Registration Card: Roy Elmer Beck, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Stock Certificate: Texas Electric Railroad Company, 1928 May 26 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Timecards and Ticket Rates: Texas Electric Railway Company, 1936-1940 (Box 1, Folder 7)